Office of the President Jill Ker Conway Files, 1974-1985
Smith College Archives
Office of the President Jill Ker Conway Files
1974-1985
Conway, Jill K., 1934-
RG 32 UUID:f8a9961b-d5e2-466e-8374-f8d87b84290f
226 boxes (95 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Author, professor, and the first female president of Smith College who pledged "...to foster research and the creation of new knowledge about matters of central importance in women's lives" by helping to develop and fund women-centered projects such as the Smith Management Program, Ada Comstock Program, and Project on Women and Social Change. Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence, reports and working papers, newspaper clippings and photographs.
Jill Ker Conway was the first female president of the college. Her selection, a watershed in the history of Smith, was also a hallmark in an era of significant change in the perception of women and their role in society. In her inaugural address, she stressed the importance of not only supporting women through their undergraduate education, but furthering the college mission "...to foster research and the creation of new knowledge about matters of central importance in women's lives." Some of the most significant accomplishments of her tenure reflect this vision. She focused much of her energy on developing and funding women-centered projects such as the Smith Management Program, Ada Comstock Program, and Project on Women and Social Change.
Conway was only 39 years old when she accepted the Smith appointment in 1974. A native of New South Wales, Australia, she received her undergraduate education at the University of Sydney (1958). Two years after completing her B.A., she left Australia to pursue her Ph.D. at Harvard University. While at Harvard, she met and married John Conway, a Canadian historian and a native of Toronto. Together they moved to Canada where both obtained positions at the University of Toronto. Jill Conway remained at the University of Toronto for more than ten years, beginning in 1964. She began as a professor of U.S. social and intellectual history, then gradually rose through the administrative ranks to serve as the vice-president for internal affairs (1973-1975).
Conway assumed the Smith presidency in July 1975. Several administrative and curricular changes were enacted during her tenure. Administrative offices, such as the Career Development Office (previously the Vocational Office), Dean of the College, Dean of Students, and Public Relations, were reorganized. The Women's Studies, Comparative Literature, Peace and War Studies, and Engineering Dual Degree programs were added to the curriculum during this period, and academic minors were introduced.
Lasting physical reminders of her presidency include the Ainsworth Gym, expanded outdoor athletic facilities, as well as renovation and additions to Neilson Library. The Alumnae Gymnasium was also renovated during this period, and became home to the Smith College Archives, the Sophia Smith Collection, and the Nonprint Resource Center.
Following her departure from the college in 1985, Conway has been a visiting professor in MIT's Program in Science, Technology, and Society. She has also authored and edited a number of books of fiction and nonfiction. Three volumes of her memoirs provide detailed biographical information about Conway. The third volume (released October 2001), chronicles her years at Smith. While this volume deals with Conway's personal as well as professional development, and is admittedly from a singular perspective, it can serve as a guide to the major developments of Smith College during her tenure.
The Conway Files include approximately 95 linear feet (226 document boxes) of material dating from 1974-1985. Some material has been restricted according the College Archives policies. The open records (154 document boxes/ 64.5 linear feet) include incoming and outgoing correspondence, reports and working papers, newspaper clippings and photographs. For more specific information about the contents of the collection see the series descriptions and folder listing below. See the Subject Guide on pages 9-12 of this finding aid for a list of topics of a broad nature.
Additional material in the Smith College Archives about the Conway era may be found in the records of other departments and offices of the college, as well as in the personal papers of Jill Ker Conway. The central secondary literature on Smith's Conway era comes from Conway herself. She has authored a number of articles and full-length works on her professional and intellectual development, which amply describe her evolving perceptions on the intersections of women's education, history and feminism. Even a cursory internet search yields a wealth of biographical information about Conway, as well as details and commentary on her literary career and continuing involvement with women's education. See the list of publications in the finding aid for Conway's personal papers for a comprehensive list of publications.
Subject Guide
The Subject Guide is meant as a supplement to information provided in the Series Descriptions and Folder Listing, and is in no way intended as a comprehensive listing of significant subject matter in the collection.
Computers
-General
Series IV. Administrative Issues
-Telecommunications
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Academic Computer Center
-Administrative Information Systems
Series IX. Committees & Boards
-Academic Computing
-Administrative Information Systems Policy Committee
-Electronic Equipment Study Group
-Word Processing Committee
Series XV. Non-Smith Organizations
-IBM
-New England Regional Computer Program [NERCOMP]
-E-mail
Series XV. Non-Smith Organizations
-COFHE (The first use of email in the president's office may have been in 1983, in a "receive-only" program via Stanford for COFHE.)
Gender
-General
Series VIII. Colleges & Universities
-Mt. Holyoke-Smith-Mt. Holyoke Institute for Research on Women's Experience and Public Policy
Series IX. Committees & Boards
-Recruitment and Retention of Women Faculty, Ad-hoc Ctte
-Research Program on Women, Ad-hoc Committee to Design a
-Status of Women and Men, Committee on the
Series XII. Faculty & Staff
-Faculty Women-Equal Opportunity Employment
Series XIV. Intercollegiate Associations
-Seven Sisters-Seven College Research Project on Careers of Women Scholars
-Special Projects Funding-Women & Social Change Project
Series V. Administrative Offices-Development-Foundations
-Ford Foundation
-Mellon Foundation
-Rockefeller Foundation
-Special Projects Funding-Miscellaneous
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Development-Foundations-Ford Foundation, re: funding for research on the career of women scholars
-Development-Foundations-Educational Foundation of America, re: the Kilbourne Sex Role Stereotypes Project
-Development-Foundations-Educational Foundation of America and the Hewlett Foundation, re: Teen Sex and Pregnancy Research
-Women's Education-General
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Admissions-Bassin Project to Improve Admissions
-Development-Foundations-Rockefeller Fdn (1980-1983), re: research funding on single-sex colleges and equal protection laws
Series VIII. Colleges & Universities
-Amherst College
-Brown University
Series XIV. Intercollegiate Associations
-Seven Sisters
-Women's College Coalition
-Women's Education-Special Projects Funding
-Ada Comstock Scholars
Series V. Administrative Offices-Development-Corporations
-Carnegie Corporation
-Chesebrough-Pond's
-Connecticut Bank and Trust
-Connecticut General Life
-Connecticut Mutual Life
-Conoco, Inc.
-Continental Group
-Covenant Life Insurance
-Dart Industries, Inc.
-Delaware North Companies, Inc.
-Hublein, Inc.
-IBM
-Kollmorgen Corporation
-Kraft, Inc.
Series V. Administrative Offices-Development-Foundations
-Educational Foundation of America
-Ford Foundation
-Mott Foundation
-Smith Management Program
Series V. Administrative Offices-Development-Corporations
-Chemical Bank
-Connecticut Bank and Trust
-Dart Industries, Inc.
-General Telephone and Electronics
-Morgan Guaranty Trust Co.
Series V. Administrative Offices-Development-Foundations
-Donner Foundation
-Exxon Education Foundation
-Hewlett Foundation
-Revlon Foundation, Inc.
-Sloan Foundation
Iranian Hostage Crisis
Series XI. Events
-President's House Events, for a dinner invitation to Iranian students, 14 Nov 1979
Lesbianism
Series II. Academic Departments
-Sociology & Anthropology, April 26, 1976 memo re student project
Series III. Academic Programs
-Junior Year Abroad-Geneva, September 8, 1983 memo and attached report
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Admissions-Bassin Project to Improve Admissions
-Dean of the College-General, for correspondence regarding Sessions House, October 7, 1982
-Dean of the College-Associate Dean for Student Affairs, for correspondence regarding Lamont House (28 Nov 1979), as well as Sessions, Parsons and other related incidents (Oct-Feb 1983).
-Personnel-Unions, for 21 Jun 1983 memo re: non-discriminatory hiring policies
-Public Relations, for response to May 1981 Boston Globe article
Series VI. Alumnae
-Alumnae Association-Alumnae Council (1982-1983)
-Smith Alumnae for Alternatives
Series IX. Committees & Boards
-Student Affairs, Committee on, for minutes of 15 Feb 1977 meeting.
Series XVI. Speeches
-Smith Alumnae Council (14 Oct 1982)
Race
-General
Series VIII. Colleges & Universities
-Amherst College (April 1979)
Series IX. Committees & Boards
-Afro-American Studies Advisory Committee
-Recruitment and Retention of Minority Faculty, Ad-hoc Ctte to Study
Series XII. Faculty & Staff
-Black Faculty and Administrators
-Fellowships-Mendenhall Fellowships
Series XIV. Intercollegiate Associations
-Five Colleges-Racism
-Society Organized Against Racism
Series XV. Non-Smith Organizations
-Consortium on Financing Higher Education (1979-1980) for info re: 1979 conference on minorities on campus
-South Africa and South African Students:
Series IV. Administrative Issues
-South Africa
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Development-Corporations-Carnegie Corporation (1979)
Series XIV. Intercollegiate Associations
-Five Colleges-South Africa
Series XV. Non-Smith Organizations-Institute of International Education
-Students of Color
Series III. Academic Programs
-Bridge Program
-Intermediate School 201 (I.S. 201)
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Admissions-Minority Students
-Dean of the College-Assistant to the Dean for Minority Affairs
-Dean of Students-Assistant to the Dean for Minority Students
Series XIV. Intercollegiate Associations
-Seven Sisters-Seven College Study-"Racial Comparisons for All Women in the Classes of 1981 and 1984"
Series XVII. Students
-Asian Students Association
-Black Students' Alliance
-Organizations-Recreation Council, 1982
Rape
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Dean of the College, for information on rape awareness workshops and security measures
Records Management
Series IV. Administrative Issues
-Administrative Structure (1976)
Series IX. Committees & Boards
-Communications & Record-Keeping Study Group
This collection is organized into eighteen series:
I. Biography
II. Academic Departments
III. Academic Programs
IV. Administrative Issues
V. Administrative Offices
VI. Alumnae
VII. Buildings and Grounds
VIII. Colleges and Universities
IX. Committees and Boards
X. Engagements
XI. Events
XII. Faculty & Staff
XIII. Graduate Work
XIV. Intercollegiate Associations
XV. Non-Smith Organizations
XVI. Speeches
XVII. Students
XVIII. Photographs
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The bulk of the collection (154 document boxes, or approximately 64.5 linear feet) is open to researchers according to the regulations of the College Archives. Another 72 document boxes (30 linear feet) are currently open only to employees of the office of origin.
Additions to the Collection
The Records of the Office of the President constitute a continuing collection, because certain materials remain in active use by the office for periods exceeding a president's actual tenure. The College Archives may receive accessions/additions long after the date of creation. Significant additions will be noted in an updated finding aid
History of the Collection
The majority of the Conway records were transferred to the College Archives from the Office of the President in a number of accessions dating from the time of her tenure until the present. Some material, however, came from Conway herself after her departure in 1985. Additional biographical materials, such as newspaper clippings, press releases, and photographs, have been added by the College Archives staff.
Search Terms
Conway, Jill K., 1934-; Smith College--Presidents.; Smith College. Office of President.
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional material in the Smith College Archives about the Conway era may be found in the records of other departments and offices of the college, as well as in the personal papers of Jill Ker Conway. The central secondary literature on Smith's Conway era comes from Conway herself. She has authored a number of articles and full-length works on her professional and intellectual development, which amply describe her evolving perceptions on the intersections of women's education, history and feminism. Even a cursory internet search yields a wealth of biographical information about Conway, as well as details and commentary on her literary career and continuing involvement with women's education. See the list of publications in the finding aid for Conway's personal papers for a comprehensive list of publications.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHY*, (2.5 document boxes / 1.0 linear feet)
  The records in this series include newspaper clippings, press releases, and correspondence relating to Conway's appointment, presidency and retirement. Included with the material about her appointment are a series of subject files she compiled while preparing to take office. These files offer an interesting perspective on the priorities of various college officials, departments and offices, as well as Conway herself. There is also information in this series about Conway's husband, John Conway, and a 1996 student paper about the official presidential portrait painted by Sarah Swenson.
  More extensive biographical material can be found in Jill Ker Conway's personal papers, as well as her published works. [There is additional oversized material from this series stored separately. Ask College Archivist for Flat Files list.]
  - Appointment (Box 1)
    - -General 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - -Congratulations
      - -Alumnae 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - -College and University Presidents 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - -Smith Faculty and Staff 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - -Toronto People 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - -Miscellaneous 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - -Preparations
      - -General 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - -Correspondence with President Mendenhall (Box 1, Folder 8)
        See also Series XII. Faculty & Staff-Emeritus Presidents & Their Families1974-1975
      - -Handwritten Notes Summer 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - -Subject Files
        - -Admissions 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - -Alumnae 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - -College Planning & Resources Committee 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - -Colleges & Universities 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - -Continuing Education 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - -Curriculum 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - -Development
          - -General 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
          - -Catholic Chaplaincy 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
          - -New York Meeting 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
          - -Toronto Meeting 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - -Faculty 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - -Financial Reports 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - -International Women's Year 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - -Libraries 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - -Museum of Art 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - -Non-Smith Organizations 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - -Northampton 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - -Physical Education 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        - -Public Relations 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - -Students 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - -Tenure and Promotion 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - -Visits
        - -November 25-26, 1974 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
        - -February 20 - March 1, 1975 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - -April 21-23, 1975 1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Family 1975-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Official Portrait by Sarah Swenson 1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Publicity
    See also Series IV. Administrative Issues-Media Coverage -and- Series V. Administrative Offices-Public Relations
    - -Articles by Jill Ker Conway 1977-1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - -Newspaper Clippings 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - -Newspaper Clippings 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - -Newspaper Clippings 1979-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - -Newspaper Releases 1975-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Retirement
    - -General 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - -Conway Celebration Day
      - -Planning 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - -Newspaper Clippings and Programs 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - -Correspondence 1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous 1974-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- SERIES II. ACADEMIC DEPARTMENTS, (10 document boxes / 4.2 linear feet)
  The files in this series are arranged alphabetically by the most recent name of the department.
  Included are newspaper clippings, correspondence, and reports from the undergraduate departments of the college. Also included are programs administered by the departments. For example, files from the Smith College Day Schools are included as a sub-series of the Department of Education. However, undergraduate and graduate academic programs administered either jointly by two or more departments, or by a separate and autonomous college office, are filed either with Academic Programs or Administrative Offices. Graduate Programs are filed in the Graduate Work series. Information about Five College joint academic programs in several areas of study can be found in the Intercollegiate Associations series.
  - General 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - -Support Staffing 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - -Triennial Reviews 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Afro-American Studies 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Afro-American Studies 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Afro-American Studies 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Art 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Art 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Art 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Athletics: Series XVII. Students-Athletics (Box 1)
  - Classics 1975-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Computer Science 1978-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dance
    - -General 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - -Triennial Review 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - East Asian Languages & Literature 1975-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Economics 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Economics 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Economics 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Education & Child Study
    See also Series IX. Cttes & Bds-Child Study Committee
    - -General 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - -General 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - -General 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - -General 1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - -General 1984-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - -Campus School 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - -Campus School 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - -Campus School 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - -Campus School Jan-May 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - -Campus School Jun-Dec 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - -Campus School Jan-Jun 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - -Campus School Jul-Dec 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - -Campus School 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - -Campus School 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - -Campus School 1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - -Campus School Jan-May 1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - -Campus School Jun-Dec 1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - -Campus School 1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - -Infant Care Center
      - -General 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - -Initial Proposal 1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - English
    - -General 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - -General 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - -General 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - -Writers-in-Residence 1976-1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Exercise & Sport Studies
    See also Series IX. Cttes & Bds.-Physical Education, Ad-hoc Committee on -and Series XVII. Students-Athletics
    - -General 1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - -General Jan-Aug 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - -General Sep-Dec 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - -General 1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - -General 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - -General 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - -General 1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - -General 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - -General 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - -Department Evaluation 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - -Evaluation Report Dec 1980 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - -Curriculum Proposal 1981 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - French 1975-1983 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - French 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - German 1975-1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Government 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Government 1980-1984 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - History
    - -General 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - -General 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - -Smith College Studies in History 1975-1984 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Italian
    - -General 1975-1984 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - -Borgese Celebration 1981, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Languages 1976-1981 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Mathematics
    - -General 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - -General 1977-1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - -Wesleyan Math Clinic 1976 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Music
    - -General 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - -General 1978-1982 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - -General 1983-1985 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - -Chamber Singers 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - -Chamber Singers 1978-1985 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - -Glee Club 1976-1984 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - -Vladimir Tropp/Rachnmaninoff Celebration 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Philosophy
    - -General 1975-1985 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - -Society for Women in Philosophy 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Psychology 1975-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Psychology 1980-1985, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Religion & Biblical Literature
    - -General 1975-1980 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - -General 1981-1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - -Excavation at Tell el-Hesi 1975-1984 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Russian Language & Literature 1975-1983 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Sciences
    See also Series III. Academic Programs-History of Science -and- Series VII. Bldgs & Grounds-Clark Science Center -and Cttes & Boards-Science Cttes
    - -Astronomy 1975-1984, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - -Biology
      - -General 1975-1981 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - -General 1982-1985 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - -National Academy of Sciences-Blakeslee Fund 1975-1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - -National Academy of Sciences-Blakeslee Fund 1980-1984 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - -Chemistry 1975-1981 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - -Chemistry 1982-1985 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - -Geology 1975-1983 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - -Geology 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - -Physics 1975-1984 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Sociology & Anthropology 1975-1980 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Sociology & Anthropology 1981-1985 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Spanish & Portuguese 1975-1984, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Theatre
    - -General 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - -General 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - -General 1979 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - -General 1980-1982 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - -General 1983-1984, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - -Black Theatre 1975-1983 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - -Film 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - -Film-Committee to Save the Film Production Course 1976 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - -"Review of Administrative Practices and Procedures" 1977 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - -Smith Ensemble Theatre 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 10)